Kaufmann Industrial Design Award Records
Kaufmann Industrial Design Award Records
1931-1962
Kaufmann, Edgar, 1910-1989.
25.0 linear ft.
The Kaufmann Industrial Design Award was administered by the Institute of International Education and sponsored by the Edgar Kaufmann Foundation to give public recognition to accomplishments in all fields of design and to encourage enterprising design developments. The award was discontinued in 1967. The collection includes correspondence, published material, films, tapes, and photographs relating to design awards candidates.
149096
Biographical History
Edgar Kaufmann, Jr. (1910-1989) was an American industrial designer, architect and artist. He apprenticed with Frank Lloyd Wright (1933-1934) and his father, Edgar Kaufmann, Sr., commissioned Fallingwater from noted architect Frank Lloyd Wright in 1936. Among his other accomplishments, he was director of the industrial design department at the Museum of Modern Art (1946-1955) and worked to encourage uniform standards for industrial design education.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from information found in the "People" section of the Industrial Design Society of America's website, http://www.idsa.org.]
The Kaufmann Industrial Design Award was administered by the Institute of International Education and sponsored by the Edgar Kaufmann Foundation to give public recognition to accomplishments in all fields of design and to encourage enterprising design developments. The award was discontinued in 1967.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Kaufmann Industrial Design Award Records contains material relating to candidates for the award from 1960-1962.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is subdivided by year and within that arranged chronologically by name of candidate. Duplicate material and oversize material is filed at the end of the collection.
Related Material
has the papers of numerous noted industrial designers and related organizations. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Edgar Kaufmann Foundation.; Institute of International Education (New York, N.Y.); Kaufmann Industrial Design Award.; Industrial design -- Awards.; Industrial designers.; Correspondence.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Awards candidates
  - 1960
    - Albini, Franco (Box 1)
    - Artex Studio and Alrar Aalto (Box 1)
    - Bill, Max (Box 1)
    - The Braun Co. and Hans Gugelot (Box 1)
    - Clusellas Gerado (Argentina) (Box 1)
    - Dreyfuss, Henry (Box 1)
    - Eames, Charles (Box 1)
    - Franck, Kai (Box 2)
    - Jacobsen, Arne (Box 2)
    - Juhl, Finn (Box 2)
    - Konzern, Kahla (H. Loffelhardt) (Box 2)
    - Knoll International Ltd. and Eero Saarinen (Box 2)
    - Kovar, Zdenek (Box 3)
    - Lindberg, Stig (Box 3)
    - Loewy, Raymond (Box 3)
    - Ponti, Gio (Box 3)
    - Proure, Jean (Box 3)
    - Rinascente compasso d'oro (Box 3)
    - Rinascente compasso d'oro (Box 4)
    - Sarpanera, Timo (Box 4)
    - Le Signe d'or industrial (Box 4)
    - Wadiraj, D. (India) (Box 4)
    - Wagenfeld, Wilhelm (Box 4)
    - Wegner, Hans (Box 5)
    - Wirkkala, Tapio (Box 5)
  - 1961
    - Albers, Josef (Box 5)
    - Arnold, John (Box 5)
    - Bayer, Herbert (Box 5)
    - Belgiojoso-Peressutti-Rogers (Box 6)
    - Bill, Max (Box 6)
    - Black, Misha (Box 6)
    - Breuer, Marcel (Box 6)
    - Cranbrook Academy of Art (Box 6)
    - Fuller, R. Buckminister (Box 6)
    - Gropius, Walter (Box 6)
    - Herlow, Eric (Box 6)
    - Hochschule Fuer Gestaltung, ULM (Box 6)
    - Institute of Design (Illinois Institute of Technology) (Box 6)
    - Itten, Johannes (Box 7)
    - Katvolos, William (Box 7)
    - Kepes, Gyorgy (Box 7)
    - Leeds College of Art (Basic Research) (Box 7)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology School of Architecture and Planning (Box 7)
    - Mies Van Der Rohe (Box 7)
    - Nelson, George (Box 7)
    - Pratt Institute (School of Industrial Design) (Box 8)
    - Rigby, Ivan (Box 8)
    - Royal College of Art, London (Box 8)
    - Scholl, Inge Aicher (Box 8)
    - Syracuse University (School of Art) (Box 9)
    - Istituto Universitario di Architettura di Venezia (Box 9)
  - 1962
    - Alcoa (Box 10)
    - Alcoa, Cupples Products (Box 10)
    - Alcoa, Wear-Ever Products (Box 10)
    - Alcoa exhibits
    - Arabia (Box 10)
    - Ar-Flex (S.P.A.) (Box 12)
    - Braun, Max (Box 12)
    - Braun, Max (Box 13)
    - British European Airways (BEA) (Box 13)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS)
      - Materials List (Box 13)
      - Materials list, oversize (Oversize 1)
      - Design examples (Oversize 3)
    - Container Corporation of America (CCA) (Box 13)
    - Container Corporation of America, oversize, 4 items
    - De Cirkel (Box 13)
    - De Cirkel (Box 14)
    - Facit Group (A.B. Atvidabergs Industrier) (Box 14)
    - Fritz Hansens Eftfl (Box 14)
    - General Motors Corporation (GMC) (Box 14)
    - Gustavsberg (Box 15)
    - IBM Corporation (Box 15)
    - Kartell S.R. L. (Box 15)
    - Knoll Associates, Inc.
      - Knoll International, Inc. (Box 16)
      - Knoll Associates, Inc. oversize, 1 item
    - La Societe KORES (Box 16)
    - La Societe KORES, oversize, 1 item
    - La Mondiale (Box 17)
    - Herman Miller, Inc., 1 item
    - Olivetti and Co., S.p.A., 2 items (Oversize 1, 2)
    - Orient Line (Box 17)
    - Orient Line, oversize, 1 item
    - Orrefors (Box 17)
    - Orrefors, oversize, 1 item
    - Penguin Books, Ltd. (Box 18)
    - Pott, C. Hugo (Box 18)
    - Venini, S.p.A. (Box 19)
    - Wohnedarf (Box 19)
- Duplicate material
  - Albini, Franc, 1960 (Box 20)
  - Alcoa, 1962 (Box 20)
  - Alcoa, Cupples Products, 1962 (Box 20)
  - Alcoa, Wear-Ever Products, 1962 (Box 20)
  - Arabia, 1962 (Box 21)
  - Ar-Flex, 1962 (Box 21)
  - Artex Studio and Alrar Aalto, 1960 (Box 21)
  - Bill, Max, 1960 (Box 21)
  - Bill, Max, 1961 (Box 21)
  - The Braun Company and Hans Gugelot, 1960 (Box 22)
  - Braun, Max, 1962 (Box 22)
  - Braun, Max, 1962 (Box 23)
  - CBS (Columbia Broadcasting System), 1962; list of materials (Box 24)
  - CBS, oversize, 1962; list of materials (Oversize 2)
  - Container Corporation of America, 1962 (Box 24)
  - Container Corporation of America, 1962 (Box 25)
  - Container Corporation of America, 1962; 8 items
  - De Cirkel, 1962 (Box 25)
  - Dreyfuss, Henry, 1960 (Box 25)
  - Eames, Charles, 1960 (Box 25)
  - Franck, Kaj, 1960 (Box 25)
  - Fritz Hansens Eftfl, 1962 (Box 26)
  - General Motors Corporation (GMC), 1962 (Box 26)
  - Gustavsberg, 1962 (Box 26)
  - Gustavsberg, 1962 (Box 27)
  - Herlow, Eric, 1961 (Box 28)
  - Jacobsen, Arne, 1960 (Box 28)
  - Juhl, Finn, 1960 (Box 29)
  - Knoll International, Ltd., and Eero Saarinen, 1960 (Box 29)
  - Kovar, Zdenek, 1960 (Box 29)
  - Leeds College of Art (Basic Research), 1961 (Box 29)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1961 (Box 29)
  - Herman Miller, Inc., 1962; 2 items
  - Orient Line, 1962; 1 item
  - Orrefors, 1962; 4 items
  - Penguin Books, Ltd., 1962 (Box 30)
  - Ponti, Gio, 1960 (Box 30)
  - Proure, Jean, 1960 (Box 30)
  - Royal College of Art, London, 1961 (Box 30)
  - Sarpanera, TiMO, 1960 (Box 31)
  - Wegner, Hans, 1960 (Box 31)
  - Wirkkala, Tapio, 1960 (Box 31)
  - Wohnedarf, 1962 (Box 31)